# **RODRIGO LIMA PEREIRA**

#### PhD IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

37 North Street ◊ nº 4 ◊ Águas Claras 71919-360 ◊ Brasília/DF ◊ Brazil +55(85)997970656 ◊ rodrigolp17@gmail.com

#### **PROFILE**

PhD in Mechanical Engineering from the University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Master of Mechanical Sciences from the University of Brasília (UnB), and Bachelor of Mechanical Engineering from the Federal University of Ceará (UFC), with a Sandwich period at the University of Nottingham (UoN), United Kingdom. Experienced researcher in various areas of engineering, with a special interest for computational mechanics, and applications involving finite elements and topology optimization in the design of smart materials and structures. He has published academic articles in international peer-reviewed journals, atended to congresses, conferences, symposia and workshops of the field, with publication of works, and acted as an academic reviewer. He has experience in teaching Dynamics, Solid Mechanics, Maintenance of Systems, and Product Design and Development.

#### **EDUCATION**

## University of Campinas - UNICAMP

2018 - 2023

PhD in Mechanical Engineering - Solid Mechanics and Mechanical Design

Campinas, SP

- · Member of the Laboratory of Topology Optimization and Multiphysics Analysis
- · Member of the Center for Computing in Engineering & Sciences
- · Scholarship from Coordination of Superior Level Staff Improvement CAPES

#### University of Brasília – UnB

2016 - 2018

Master of Mechanical Sciences

Brasília, DF

- · Member of the Fatigue, Fracture and Materials Group
- · Scholarship from Coordination of Superior Level Staff Improvement CAPES

### Federal University of Ceará – UFC

2012 - 2016

Bachelor of Mechanical Engineering

Fortaleza, CE

- · Outstanding Academic Performance Award Engineer's Day, 2016
- · Science Without Borders Program scholarship recipient

## **COMPLEMENTARY EDUCATION**

## University of Nottingham – UoN

2013 - 2014

Sandwich Period in Mechanical Engineering (BEng) – Science Without Borders Program

Nottingham, UK

· Scholarship from National Council for Scientific and Technological Development – CNPq

## Virtual University of the State of São Paulo - UNIVESP

August 2021 - December 2021

Courses on Didactic-Pedagogical Processes in Distance Learning

Online

- · Learning Strategies for Pedagogical Mediation 40h
- · Learning Assessment: Elaboration of Assessment Instruments 40h

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### University of Nottingham - UoN

Part-time Researcher

June 2014 - August 2014

Nottingham, UK

· Research Project: CFD Analysis and Design of Landspeed Record Car Body

### Companhia Brasileira de Bebidas das Américas – AMBEV

April 2015 - June 2015

People and Management Intern

Fortaleza, CE

· Management of time banks, vacations and compensation of sectoral employees

Gerdau Aços Longos S/A

2015 - 2016

Project Engineering Intern

Fortaleza, CE

- · Develop, execute and control engineering projects, as well as support maintenance activities
- · Take part in internal courses of project management, safety, environment, social responsibility and maintenance

## University of Brasília - UnB

2016 - 2018

Master's Researcher

Brasília, DF

- · Researcher of the field of fatigue and fracture of materials, with emphasis on uniaxial and fretting fatigue, mechanical contact and finite elements
- · Research Project: Predicting the Fatigue Life Under Fretting Conditions of an 1350-H19 Aluminum Wire Using the Finite Element Method

## University of Campinas - UNICAMP

2018 - 2023

PhD Researcher and Teaching Intern

Campinas, SP

- Member of the Teaching Internship Program (PED), working on the courses of Dynamics (2S/2019) and Solid Mechanics (1S/2020). Responsible for the preparation and correction of tests, computer codes, and didactic exercises, as well as for teaching extra or substitute classes
- · Researcher of the field of solid mechanics and mechanical design, focusing on evolutionary methods of topology optimization, finite elements and acoustic-porous systems
- · Research Project: Multimaterial and Multidomain Acoustic Topology Optimization Based on an Evolutionary Approach

## Virtual University of the State of São Paulo - UNIVESP

August 2021 - December 2021

Teacher Facilitator

Online

• Teacher facilitator of Maintenance of Systems (3B/2021), and Product Design and Development (4B/2021). Responsible for the correction of tests and didactic exercises, as well as for teaching extra classes

#### Scientific Journal Reviewer

2022 - Current

- · Finite Elements in Analysis and Design
- · 8th International Symposium on Solid Mechanics

#### **Boards and Judging Commissions**

2019 - 2021

Scientific Projects Evaluator

Multiple Locations

- · XXVII Scientific Initiation Congress, 2019. University of Campinas
- · XXIX Scientific Initiation Congress, 2021. University of Campinas
- · 11ª BRAGANTEC Science and Technology Fair, 2021. Federal Institute of São Paulo

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Programming Languages Matlab, Python, LATEX

**Software** Abaqus, Comsol Multiphysics, GIT, Inkscape

Frameworks & Libraries Jupyter Notebooks, LiveLink, Matplotlib, Numpy, Scipy

#### **LANGUAGES**

Native Portuguese Fluent English Beginner French

#### **AWARDS AND RECOGNITION**

## Federal University of Ceará – UFC

2016

Undergraduate Award Fortaleza, CE

· Outstanding Academic Performance Award – Engineer's Day, 2016

Science Olympiads 2007 - 2009

High School Awards Fortaleza, CE

- · Bronze Medal Brazilian Olympiad of Astronomy and Astronautics (OBA/SAB) 2008 and 2009
- · Bronze Medal Brazilian Olympiad of Physics (OBF/SBF) 2007 and 2008
- · Silver Medal Brazilian Olympiad of Robotics (OBR/SBC-SBA) 2008

#### **COMPLEMENTARY ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES**

# IV Career's Fair – Federal University of Ceará 2012

Vocational Guidance Counselor Fortaleza, CE

## **English Course** 2011 - 2013

House of British Culture of the Federal University of Ceará Fortaleza, CE

· Workload: 300 h

## Test of English as a Foreign Language - TOEFL iBT

2013

Total score: 87 Fortaleza, CE

## CCES Workshop Internacional - 2019

2019

Poster: Acoustical Topology Optimization Applied to Rigid Noise Barriers Águas de Lindoia, SP

e-Forum Acusticum 2020

Presentation: Design of Periodic Noise Barriers Using the Bi-directional Evolutionary Optimization Method Lyon, FR

# 15th World Congress on Computation Mecchanics & 8th Asian Pacific Congress on Computation Mechanics

Presentation: Topology Optimization of Acoustic-Poroelastic-Elastic Structures for Sound Attenuation 2022 – Kyoto, JP

## 8th International Symposium on Solid Mechanics

2022 – Campinas, SP

Presentation: Topology Optimization Design of Multilayered Acoustic-Poroelastic-Elastic Structures by the BESO Approach

#### CCES Workshop Internacional – 2022

2022

Presentation: Evolutionary Topology Optimization to Design Multiphase Soundproof Systems

Itatiba, SP

Master's Thesis 2018

University of Brasília – UnB

Brasília, DF

· Pereira, Rodrigo Lima. Predição da Vida em Fadiga Sob Condições de Fretting de um Fio de Alumínio 1350-H19 Utilizando o Método dos Elementos Finitos. 2018. Dissertação (Mestrado em Ciências Mecânicas), Universidade de Brasília, Brasília, Brasília, Brasília,

Doctoral Dissertation 2023

University of Campinas - UNICAMP

Campinas, SP

· Pereira, Rodrigo Lima. Multimaterial and Multidomain Acoustic Topology Optimization Based on an Evolutionary Approach. 2023. Thesis (Ph.D.). School of Mechanical Engineering, University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil.

### Articles Published in Scientific Journals

2020 - 2023

- · Pereira, R. L., Díaz, J. I. M., Ferreira, J. L. A. et al. Numerical and experimental analysis of fretting fatigue performance of the 1350-H19 aluminum alloy. J. Braz. Soc. Mech. Sci. Eng. v.42, p.419 (2020)
- · Pereira, R. L., Lopes, H. N., Pavanello, R. Topology optimization of acoustic systems with a multiconstrained BESO approach. Finite Elem. Anal. Des. v.201, p.103701 (2022)
- · Pereira, R. L., Lopes, H. N., Moura, M. S., Pavanello R. Multi-domain acoustic topology optimization based on the BESO approach: applications on the design of multi-phase material mufflers. Struct. Multidiscipl. Optim. v.66, p.25 (2023)
- · Pereira, R. L., Anaya-Jaimes L. M, Pavanello R. Evolutionary topology optimization approach to design multiphase soundproof systems with poroelastic media. *Under Review*: Finite Elem. Anal. Des. (2023)

#### Articles Published in Annals of Events

2018 - 2022

- · Lima Pereira, R., Monroy, J. I, Ferreira, J. L. A. Fadiga Uniaxial de um Fio de Alumínio 1350-H19 Utilizando o Método dos Elementos Finitos, in: X Congresso Nacional de Engenharia Mecânica, Salvador/BR (2018)
- · Pereira, R. L., Anaya-Jaimes, L. M., Pavanello, R. Design of periodic noise barriers using the bi-directional evolutionary optimization method, in: Forum Acusticum, Lyon/FR (2020)
- · Pereira R. L., Anaya-Jaimes L. M., Pavanello R. Topology Optimization of Acoustic-Poroelastic-Elastic Structures for Sound Attenuation, in: 15th World Congress on Computation Mecchanics & 8th Asian Pacific Congress on Computation Mechanics, Kyoto/JP (2022)
- · Pereira, R. L., Pavanello, R. Topology Optimization Design of Multilayered Acoustic-Poroelastic-Elastic Structures by the BESO Approach, in: 8th International Symposium on Solid Mechanics, Campinas/BR (2022)